<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon of the saints judging the world. Preached at the Assizes holden in Huntingdon, March 13. 1648. by John Gaule, Minister of the Word in Great Staughton.</title>
            <author>Gaule, John, 1604?-1687.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85868</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G380</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E549_8</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205625</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864948</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864948</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117181</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85868)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117181)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 85:E549[8])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon of the saints judging the world. Preached at the Assizes holden in Huntingdon, March 13. 1648. by John Gaule, Minister of the Word in Great Staughton.</title>
                  <author>Gaule, John, 1604?-1687.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 27, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Dring, and are to be sold at his shop at the signe of the George in Fleetstreet, near Cliffords-Inns,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill. 2.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117181:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON OF THE Saints judging the World.</p>
            <p>Preached at the Aſſizes holden in <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingdon,</hi> March 13. 1648.</p>
            <p>By <hi>John Gaule,</hi> Miniſter of the Word in Great STAVGHTON.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.2.</bibl> Doe ye not know that the Saints ſhall judge the world? and if the world ſhall be judged by you, are ye unworthy to judge the ſmalleſt matters?</q>
            <q>
               <hi>Rectè judicatur hic mundus in nobis, ſi opus perfidorum hominum non inveniatur in nobis.</hi> 
               <bibl>Ambroſ. loc.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>Thomas Dring,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the Signe of the <hi>George</hi> in <hi>Fleet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreet,</hi> near <hi>Cliffords-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> 1649.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:117181:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:117181:2"/>
            <head>To all the SAINTS.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He beſt Books have been dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to you, and to you only, <hi>Rom. 1.7. 1 Cor. 1.2. 2 Cor. 1.1. Eph. 1.1. Phil. 1.1. Col. 1.2.</hi> But ſhall I call them Dedications, or Directions? For He wrote (the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> I meane) to his Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pils, not his Patrons. And (to ſpeake betwixt ſuch us you, and ſuch as my ſelfe) He dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates nothing to you, that directs you not, how you ſhould direct your ſelves to Him, to whom you are dedicated: Or (returning to the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle</hi>) ſhall I ſay they were his Salutations, or pious Apprecations? <hi>(Grace be unto you and Peace, &amp;c.)</hi> So let them be eſteemed:
<pb facs="tcp:117181:3"/>So let this of mine be accepted. God grant you his Grace; God ſend you his Peace. It is my daily prayer for you all; who am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Leſſe then the leaſt of all Saints, JOHN GAULE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:117181:3"/>
            <head>Of the <hi>SAINTS</hi> judging the World.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Cor. 6.2.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Doe ye not know that the Saints ſhall judge the world? and if the world ſhall be judged by you, are ye un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy to judge the ſmalleſt matters?</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Text (to my apprehenſion) ſets forth the twofold Aſſizes; the Generall, and the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, or rather, the Eternall, and the Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall. The generall, and Eternall, are of <hi>the Saints judging the world:</hi> The Temporall, and Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, are about their <hi>judging in ſmaller matters.</hi> For a further light into the diſcuſſions, and iſſues of both theſe; we are now to ſcanne the Apoſtles words more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly. And therein to conſider theſe two parts of ſpeech: 1. The forme of his Interrogating; <hi>Doe ye not know,</hi> &amp;c. 2. The forme of his Inferring; <hi>And if the world ſhall,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The forme or manner of his Interrogating; which is with a vehement indignation at their ignorance or unmindfulneſſe. For alwayes, negative Interrogations in matters neceſſary, ſerve to convince and reprove with more vehemence: Convincing, that ſo it is; and reproving, becauſe it ought to be otherwiſe. But why
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:117181:4"/>ſhould the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſo eagerly indigne this their <hi>not knowing,</hi> ſince it is in a point of ſo much depth, and difficulty, as that a well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightened Saint might be (in a great part) innocently ignorant of it? Indeed, had the queſtion been about the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the exact cauſe, and preciſe forme of the <hi>Saints judging the worl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>;</hi> their ignorance had not only been pardonable, but their modeſt acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſcence in it commendable. But for as much as he enquires only upon the ſimple <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; intimating that ſuch a truth is, and ought to be beleeved by all Saints and Faithfull; there was their ignorance culpable, yea and the rather worthy of vehement and ſevere repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, for theſe following reaſons. 1. Becauſe it is not to be doubted but that they had heard the univerſall promiſe in this point (<hi>viz.</hi> that in <hi>Matthew</hi> 19.28.) Now, to be ignorant of an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall promiſe (having the meanes to underſtand it) is affected ignorance, or ignorance out of negligence; and therefore deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the ſharper increpation. 2. Becauſe he had but lately inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated ſuch a thing unto them, even in his rectifying of their raſh judgings (<hi>chap.</hi> 4. <hi>ver.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.) <hi>Judge nothing before the time, untill the Lord come,</hi> &amp;c. For when he comes, then ſhall be the time for you to judge with infallible diſcerning in your ſelves; and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the palpable deſerts of other men. 3. Becauſe he had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready declared unto them, a ſpeciall priviledge of theirs, in ſuch a caſe; which they notwithſtanding had miſprized, or neglected. As Chap. 2. ver. 15. <hi>He that is ſpirituall judgeth all things;</hi> All things neceſſarily pertaining to a naturall life, to a civill converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to a ſpirituall profeſſion, and to eternall ſalvation. <hi>Y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe is judged of no man;</hi> that is, he himſelfe, for his perſon, ſtate, conſcience (not but that his life and actions are ſubject to others judgment.) Or, judged of <hi>no man;</hi> that is, not of mans day, or more humane judgement, opinion, cenſure, &amp;c. but by the Law, and Word of God. Or, of <hi>no man;</hi> that is, of no man rightly, that is not <hi>ſpirituall,</hi> like himſelfe. For it is impoſſible that a naturall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> carnall man ſhould diſcerne of a ſpirituall mans gifts and graces: becauſe it is not the naked obſervation of ſenſe, nor the barren ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on of the mind; but the conformable inclination of the will and affections, whereby all ſanctifying graces are truly and perfectly diſcerned. Or laſtly, the ſpirituall man (as purely and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:117181:4"/>ſpirituall) is judged (or juſtly accuſed) by no man, whether carnall, or other. For to judge or argue him (on that part which neither erres, nor offends) is to judge not him; but the <hi>Spirit of God</hi> in him. Pauſe here a little, and take notice, how ignorance of this priviledge made them miſprize it, and derogate from it which alſo makes many others both to arrogate it, and to overprize them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in it. 4. Becauſe he had but immediately before evinced (from their Eccleſiaſticke, yea or domeſticke uſe and authority) that it properly belonged to them, <hi>to judge them that are within;</hi> though not <hi>them that are without,</hi> Chap. 5.12. How much leſſe then did it appertaine to them that are without, to judge them that are within? Nevertheleſſe, they (ignorant, or negligent in all theſe) had (by wilfull provocation, or appeale) betrayed their truth, to errour; their promiſe, to unbeliefe; their priviledge, to invaſion; and their peculiar jurisdiction, to common uſurpation. And not only ſo, but their cauſes to corruption, their perſons to contempt, their infirmities to deriſion, their vocation to calumny, and the whole Church of <hi>Chriſt</hi> (or Chriſtian profeſſion) to ſcandall and offence. Was there not then juſt cauſe for the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> more ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement indignation, in reproving ſuch their careleſſe and peeviſh errour?</p>
            <p>Were we to examine the like cauſes, with their like effects now adayes; it were enough to raiſe or urge an endigning and incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pating commotion in us, beyond the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> becauſe of the more exceſſive errours and exorbitances: Yea (ſet aſide all other) the blindneſſe, and abuſes, (even in this particular) were ſufficient to provoke it. For, as touching Saints, and Saints judging, men were never more ignorant; and yet never more arrogant. But (though I intend to follow the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> in his forme of interroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting) yet (perſwaded of better things in you) I ſhall (as it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hooves me) abate ſomewhat of his vehemence: and aske only in a moderation, and ſo calmely, as with ſome conceſſion to your judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the truth.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Doe ye know, who <hi>the Saints</hi> are, that ſhall judge the world? 'Tis a queſtion, and not well anſwered by all; and therefore not well knowne to all. The Papiſts are tying up the Saints here, either to thoſe of their owne making, or elſe to thoſe of their own
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:117181:5"/>marring. The judging Saints (after their judgement) are the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarks, Prophets. Apoſtles (ſay they no more but ſo? yes) the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Virgin by her ſelfe; and yet, their whole order of Virgins, Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicall men, their Doctors, Confeſſors, Martyrs; their contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plative men, perfect men, men of voluntary poverty. And for theſe they are framing ſpeciall <hi>Aureola's;</hi> not only to preferre them in their glorious ſtate, but in this judiciary act. And yet more preciſely for the men of voluntary poverty. And all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe upon <hi>Peters</hi> ſaying, <hi>Behold we have forſaken all, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed thee;</hi> Chriſt ſayes, <hi>Ye ſhall ſit upon twelve Thrones, judging the twelve Tribes,</hi> &amp;c. Mat. 19.27, 28. But (by their leave) <hi>our Saviour</hi> directs not his ſpeech to <hi>Peter</hi> only, but to all the reſt. Neither doth he now reply to their forſaking, and following (for to that he ſpeaks preciſely in the ſubſequent verſe) but to all them, <hi>that have followed him in the regeneration, viz.</hi> in the doctrine of it, and ſo are come unto the ſtate of it; are regenerate, or are Saints. Even theirs (one, as well as another) is this priviledge, this prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. It is worth the noting (how they) all of them, conſent to contradict themſelves; even in the very earneſtneſſe of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention about this preheminence. And herein they follow their owne Maſter (the Maſter of Sentences) who though he would faine determine it to ſome ſuch as before ſpoken of; yet he is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to conclude; that by thoſe fitting on the twelve Thrones, is to be underſtood an <hi>univerſitas judicantium:</hi> and ſo, by the twelve Tribes an <hi>univerſitas judicandorum.</hi> For which we are to thanke the Fathers; and neither him, nor them. I may as aptly (and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all contradiction) apply it to this Text, as he to that. As by <hi>the world</hi> here, we underſtand a collective, or an univerſallity of thoſe that ſhall be judged: ſo by <hi>the Saints,</hi> a collective alſo, or an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſallity of thoſe that ſhall judge them. Nevertheleſſe, we deny not a preheminence to ſome certaine Saints, even in this very act. For we hold it not againſt the rules of Reaſon, or Faith either, to beleeve, That thoſe Saints which are more eminent in grace, and ſo judging the world here, ſhall alſo be more eminent in glory, and ſo judging the world hereafter. Only, though we are taught to preferre them, for their ſeverall meaſures; yet we are not let to underſtand, why we ſhould there preferre one Saint before ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:117181:5"/>for their ſeverall orders onely. Our <hi>Saviour Chriſt</hi> ſpake it to all kind of Saints, <hi>ye which have followed me in the regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> and then more preciſely to his Diſciples; <hi>Ye alſo ſhall ſit, &amp;c.</hi> yet is their preheminence no barre to the priviledge of all other. The <hi>Lord</hi> commeth, not with his twelve only, but with the <hi>ten thouſands of his Saints, to execute judgement upon all, &amp;c.</hi> Jude. 14.15. Yea, as touching the <hi>executing upon them the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment written</hi> (be it temporall, as ſome Rabbines would, or ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall and eternall, as Chriſtians underſtand it) yet it followes, <hi>this honour have all his Saints,</hi> Pſal. 149.9. Thus we ſee who the Saints are in the generall; enough for expoſition: yet it remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to ſay, who, or what a Saint is in particular; but that ſhall be in the concluſion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Doe you know what <hi>the World</hi> is, that ſhall be judged by the Saints? The vulgar tranſlation, though it be redundant to the text, yet it ſeemes to be deficient to the truth: For it thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrues it <hi>(of this World)</hi> as if it were but this preſent World; and but a part alſo, or ſome appurtenance of it. But the text ſaith <hi>the World</hi> emphatically; and meanes the whole (preſent, and future,) both perſons, and actions. I could take up old tearmes, and tell you of a twofold world; a <hi>mundus perditionis,</hi> and a <hi>mundus ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vationis;</hi> a world of damned ones, and a world of ſaved ones; and both of them to be judged; The one by <hi>Chriſt</hi> alone, and the other, by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and all his Saints. And theſe ſay as much in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, as the latter received diſtinction, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f a judgement of Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution; for ſo <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe ſhall judge the Saints: and of a judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Condemnation; for ſo <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and his Saints ſhall judge the world. But I am to ſpeak of that world which the Saints ſhall judge: and ſo I may ſay, the Saints are competent judges of a threefold world; the Naturall, the Civill, and the Sinfull. 1. The Saints are apt and proper judges of the Naturall world, the world of Creatures. And that by their true and certain knowledge of their chriſtian liberty, in the lawfull uſe, and ſubordinate diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them. For where true chriſtian liberty is in any thing, there God hath left a man to be his owne judge; and he that rightly uſes it, rightly judges over thoſe things he hath a power to uſe. But he that abuſes it, makes the creatures to groane againſt him:
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:117181:6"/>and now are they his judges, and not he theirs. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. The Saints are apt and proper judges over the Civill world, or the world of men. And indeed, more apt than other men; Becauſe of their more light of univerſall truth, more rectitude of reaſon, more diſcretion of circumſtances, more tenderneſſe of conſcience, more innocence of heart and hand, more abnegated paſſions and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, more zeale to juſtice, more love of mercy, more reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with good men, and more deputation from God himſelfe; as bearing his Image (both in their perſons and places) above the reſt. 3. The Saints are the apt and proper judges againſt the ſinfull world, the world of wicked men, and reprobates; as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving firſt judged ſinne in themſelves, as having long judged them by their workes and examples, as having the gift of the diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of ſpirits, as labouring to judge exactly after the perpetuall law of God, as being witneſſes of their wretched lives, as having ſuffered at their unjuſt hands, and as minding nothing more than the glory of the ſupreme Judge himſelf. Well, as the Saints are the judges, ſo the world is alwayes the guilty party, or worthy to be judged: and therefore ſeeing they are the Saints that ſhall judge the world, let the world take heed how it takes upon it to judge the Saints: For the more preſumptuouſly or perverſly the world ſhall judge the Saints (by wiſe permiſſion) here, in this preſent life; the more adverſely and ſeverely ſhall the Saints (by juſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion) judge the world in the world to come. But caution is not for the world, but correction; let the Saints therefore ſee to it, that they goe not now beyond their commiſſion, judging the world uprightly however; and in no caſe, raſhly one another.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Doe ye know what this act of the Saints <hi>judging</hi> is? Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of it is to be learn't from the originall word, twice varied in the Text (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) both in voyce and tenſe. 1. Varied in the voice; one active, the other paſſive: and active, as from the Saints; paſſive, as upon the world: Whence I obſerve by the way, that the Saints ſhall be active onely, and the world paſſive onely in judgement. 2. Varied againe from the tenſe, or time; one a word of the future, the other (though tranſlations note it not) a word of the preſent: whereupon I obſerve againe, that the Saints ſhall not onely judge the world hereafter, but the world is already
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:117181:6"/>judged by them even in this preſent life. And verily, this ought to be regarded; for be that is not ſuch a Saint as to judge the world here, ſhall never be ſuch a Saint as to judge the world here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after: I meane if the world be not judged by him now, in his faith and profeſſion, in his heart and conſcience, in his life and example, ther's little hope that he ſhould be one elected to judge the world (by his vote and ſuffrage) at that great day. Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, for this act of judging, Some (both Papiſts and Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants) are ſcrupled at the preciſeneſſe of the act, and would have the <hi>Saints judging</hi> the <hi>world,</hi> the <hi>Angels,</hi> the <hi>twelve tribes,</hi> the <hi>ungodly, &amp;c.</hi> to be rather an hyperbolicall expreſſion, than to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie any ſuch preciſely reall action; or that this their judging ſhould import onely a kind of ſuperlative, and indefinite prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence of their ſtate in generall; and not any poſitive and determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate ſentence of ſuch an act in ſpeciall. And the reaſon for ſuch their opinion appeares to be this, leſt otherwiſe, they might ſeem to derogate, or detract from the judiciary act and office of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> But (with their peace) I muſt prove it from my Text, that if the Saints judging of the world be but allegoricall; ſo likewiſe is their judging in the ſmalleſt matters. But if the judging in the ſmalleſt matters be to be underſtood as a ſpecifique and preciſe act of judicature; ſo likewiſe is the judging of the world, or elſe the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> inference, <hi>a ſimili,</hi> or <hi>a majori,</hi> (confer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing here the one with the other, and preferring the one before the other) is not onely incongruous, or unapt, but n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l, and of no force at all. For in arguments of imparity, there muſt be ſome ſunilitude of the kind, wherein both are conſentaneous: or elſe there can be no inequality of degree, wherein the one is to be ſuppoſed to exceed the other. And as to their reaſon; the ſole property of judging, the authority, power, glory, theſe being <hi>Chriſts</hi> confeſt: and the Saints onely the aſſeſſion, aſſent, vote ſuffrage, comprobation, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation, &amp;c. Surely, this can no more derogate from Chriſts act or office, than the ſeſſion of the Juſtices, doth from the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Judge in chiefe. <hi>Chriſt</hi> is pleaſed to make them his aſſeſſors and aſſiſtants (co-operators, though not co-adjutors) in that peculiar act, both for the more ſetting forth of his own maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, and glory; for their more dignity, and comfort; and for the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:117181:7"/>others more terror, and conviction. This truth (with all theſe reaſons) appeares plaine from theſe places, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.28. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.2. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.9, 10. <hi>Jude</hi> 14.15. To which I may adde, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 149.9. <hi>Zach.</hi> 14.5.</p>
            <p>So then, that the Saints ſhall judge together with <hi>Chriſt,</hi> is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary and eaſie to believe: but how they ſhall doe it, there's the difficulty to conceive; and peradventure not much neceſſary for us, as now. For of this there's deep ſilence in the Scriptures; or elſe obſcurity deeper than ſilence it ſelfe. The moſt curious inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitors here, are driven to confeſſe, that the manner of this their preciſe acting is not to be learnt, but by divine revelation. I may ſay further (with ſome of them alſo) that it ſhall not be directly known, ere it be ſeen, and done, or (at leaſt wiſe) cannot be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly apprehended, but in the very acting of it: Yet ſince the boldneſſe of mens broaching their conceptions (in this caſe) is already begunne, (And that not without confidence even of erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious aſſertions, and impoſitions) Let me therefore be bold alſo to ſet forth ſome conceptions; leaving you to your liberty of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which of them may be more orthodox, and which of them the moſt genuine.</p>
            <p n="1">1. One is, That the Saints ſhall then judge, by preſenting their perſons; or rather, by a preſentation of their actions; compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their good examples, with the evill of the world, thereby to convince, and condemne them. This I conceive to be a truth: For ſomuch is to be collected out of <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.28. <hi>&amp;</hi> 25.35, 42. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.5, 6. &amp; 14.10. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4, 5. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10. <hi>Iude</hi> 14, 15. yet ſurely, this is not all. For if it be no more but a manifeſtation, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of their workes; thus ſhall the world judge it ſelfe, and the wicked of it work to condemne one another. For, as the worſe examples of the more wicked, are ſaid to juſtifie the ill actions of the leſſe wicked, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.51. ſo the leſſe ill actions of the leſſe wicked, ſhall then judge the worſe examples of the more wicked, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.27, 41, 42. <hi>&amp;</hi> 11.22, 24. And although there be great difference between the workes and examples of the Saints, and others; and ſo between their compariſons: yet ſhall they all agree to judge. This ſingular act therefore of the Saints judging muſt needs be ſomething more than ſo.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:117181:7"/>2. Another is, That the Saints ſhall judge by way of aſſeſſion, aſſent, vote, ſuffrage, comprobation, acclamation, and the like ſubordinate, and conformable acts. <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.28. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.137. <hi>Revel.</hi> 16.7. <hi>&amp;</hi> 19.1, 2. This alſo is a truth, and commonly ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived: yet neither is this all. For not onely the Saints are ſaved; but even the Devils, and the Damned, ſhall then be convinced, and conſtrained to acknowledge the juſtice and equity of Gods judgements. At that time (ſaith <hi>Chriſt, Rom.</hi> 14.11. <hi>Every knee ſhall bow to me, and every tongue ſhall confeſſe to God.</hi> All powers, perſons, nations, languages, conſciences (good and bad) ſhall not only be brought into a ſubjection to the power, but to the confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the juſtice of it. And albeit Angels, and Saints, ſhall doe it directly, and voluntarily; and adore, admire, and praiſe, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.10. yet the Devils, and the Damned, ſhall not be able to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract any thing from it; And therefore ſhall doe it; although it be but involuntarily, and indirectly: ſo that both their acts are thus alſo tending to judgement; and therefore that of the Saiuts muſt yet be ſomewhat elſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Another is, That the Saints, though they ſhall not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the ſentence together with <hi>Chriſt;</hi> yet they ſhall repeat it after him, or relate, and tell it unto others. This is the fond opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, expreſt and preſt ſo by the Papiſts (and by the wiſeſt of them, their Schoolmen, Summiſts, Caſuiſts) But if it be not frivolous, let them anſwer us. To whom (for Gods ſake) ſhould they tell it? To their fellow Saints, and Angels? why, they all were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with it, as well as themſelves; underſtanding it at once, by a primary and immediate revelation: and therefore need no mediate, or ſecondary information of theirs, by parts and degrees. Or to the Devils, and the Damned? what need that either, after an immediate, and totall conviction of all conſciences? And ſince (as themſelves are more inclined to believe) it ſhall be exerciſed mentally (a proper act of divine Power) to what purpoſe then ſhould there be a vocall pronuntiation, or repetition? And if the Saints have any other way to inſinuate themſelves into one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; which way elſe ſhould they doe it to the world? Or what needs any further patefaction of the divine juſtice to any, than that proportionable to every ones witneſſe within himſelfe?</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:117181:8"/>4. Another is, That the Saints ſhall judge in a petitionary way, requiring, provoking, rather invoking, or praying juſtice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the world. I dare not deny, but that there may be very truth in this, As <hi>Revel.</hi> 6.9, 10. But yet in as much as this is an act of the Saints, or <hi>Souls under the Altar;</hi> yea, and of the Saints upon the footſtoole too, <hi>Luke</hi> 18.7, 8. Me thinks the preciſe act of the Saints upon the throne, ſhould bee ſomething moreover to that.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Another is, That the Saints ſhall judge the world, as it were by way of inditing, impleading, accuſing, witneſſing, &amp;c. And (I conceive) it may be thus. The Saints of the law, more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially accuſing the breakers of the law, by the law, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.45. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.12. And the Saints of the Goſpell, more eſpecially judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the profaners of the Goſpell, by the Goſpell, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.16. But foraſmuch as theſe are the rules, and formes, whereby they accuſe them here (and accordingly have done it in all ages) ſomething aſſuredly it is, that they ſhall more formally act hereafter.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Another is, That the Saints ſhall then judge after the manner of exultation; glorying, <hi>rejoycing to ſee the vengeance,</hi> Pſal. 58.10. And that out of a perfect zeale of juſtice, void of the leaſt deſire of revenge. But nevertheleſſe, this their exulting being a conſtant and perpetuall act (here inchoate, there conſummate, not for time, but integrity) me thinks ſtill the preſent or preciſe act ſhould yet be ſomewhat more.</p>
            <p n="7">7. The laſt (and I conceive, the apteſt) is, That the Saints ſhall judge in <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the Saints. He in them, by thoſe infallible principles of divine juſtice which are impreſt in them; they in him, by thoſe inſeparable bonds of union, whereby they wholly relate to him: Or he, and they together, as Head, and Members. The act of the Head imputed to the Members, and the act of the Members acknowledged by the Head. His judiciary act (eſpecially as from his Mediatorſhip, and Manhood) having a peculiar influence upon them: and ſo their act (in a perfect con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity, though not abſolute proportion) having a peculiar re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to him. And in this conception I am not alone (others as orthodox, and more learned, ſpeak with me to this effect.) Nor are we in it without the Scriptures, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.28. <hi>Inde</hi> 14, 15.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:117181:8"/>which (ſaving to each their property) ſpeaks there of it, as one joint act. And therefore I beleeve, when <hi>Chriſts</hi> act ſhall be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly apprehended and underſtood, then ſhall this of the Saints alſo, and not before.</p>
            <p>Only ſuffer me to conclude the point in a few diſtinctive terms. 1. <hi>Cauſaliter, &amp; auctoritative,</hi> as principall Cauſe, and through ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Authority; ſo ſhall <hi>Chriſt</hi> judge alone, and neither Saints nor Angels with him. 2. <hi>Exemplariter, &amp; comparativè,</hi> by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring their actions and examples; ſo ſhall not only good men judge bad men, but bad men one another. 3. <hi>Aſſiſtenter, &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretativè,</hi> as aſſeſſors, adherers, approvers, admirers, applauders, &amp;c. So ſhall the Saints judge the world. 4. <hi>Miniſterialiter, &amp; executivè,</hi> miniſterially, and in a powerfull executing of the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, both upon the world, and the Devils; ſo ſhall the Angels alſo judge together with him, at that day.</p>
            <p n="2">II. The forme or manner of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> inferring: <hi>And if the world ſhall be judged by you, are ye unworthy to judge the ſmalleſt matters?</hi> And he inferres with an interrogation upon a ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition: indigning ſtill, that any man ſhould not eaſily ſee into the force of the conſequence, upon ſuch a Conceſſion. Yet all the weight of his inference is not ſo particularly to be apprehended from any Tranſlation, as from the originall words themſelves. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their native Emphaſis therfore we obſerve how ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he inferres:</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>A majori,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. And thus are they inforcing or affirming validly from the greater to the leſſe. If the Collective, the univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall world ſhall be judged by you, how much more then may you be Judges of the diſtributive, or a few particulars? If in things eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, how much more in things temporall? If in Cauſes betwixt God and man, how much more in matters betwixt man and man? If in thoſe the greateſt, how much more in theſe the ſmalleſt mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters?</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Ab interiori,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. We miſſe the riſe of this Argument in many tranſlations, and in moſt expoſitions. Becauſe it is uſuall (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting the Greeke Interpreters) to tranſlate, and expound this <hi>in you, by you.</hi> Notwithſtanding (under correction as touching the frequent enallage or change of certaine Particles) let me ſay;
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:117181:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>that where the originall expreſſion is cleare ſenſe, and notably ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to a deduction of ſound doctrine, there it is ſafeſt alwayes to retaine the words in their owne idiome. Now to me it ſignifies very emphatically, to read it thus; <hi>If the world be judged in your</hi> rather than thus, If the world ſhall be <hi>judged by you.</hi> For it notes a fundamentall, and intrinſecall act of judging; which excels any inſtrumentall and extrinſecall act whatſoever. And to judge ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally, in forme, and word and ſentence, is nothing ſo eſſentiall to judiciall truth, as to judge internally, in heart, in mind, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. Beſides, the originall phraſe reſerved, more properly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects either kind of Judicature. For the eternall judgement (as it is generally conceived, and upon more probabilitie) ſhall be men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, (in the execution) rather than vocall; conſiſting in Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation and conviction from within, more than in any kind of exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination or diſcuſſion from without: Therefore is it more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to ſay of the Saints there, the world ſhall be judged <hi>in you,</hi> than <hi>by you.</hi> And as for temporall Judicature, who apprehends it not to be more in a rationall and conſcientious verity, than in any verball or ſentencing formallity? And that this (even in all the exactnes) is but a formall injuſtice without that? Therefore even here alſo, the world is rather to be judged <hi>in you,</hi> than <hi>by you.</hi> And therefore I could wiſh that we were not ſo ſtrict in formes of judging <hi>by:</hi> and yet more ſtrict in grounds of judging <hi>in.</hi> For (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve it) if another be only judged <hi>by</hi> us, then are we judged <hi>in</hi> our ſelves. But I purſue the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> Argument; If the world be judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>in you,</hi> which is the greateſt matter, then may it the better be judged <hi>by you,</hi> in theſe the ſmalleſt matters. And you all (Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans and Saints) know this for a truth. He that ſo judges not the world within himſelfe, as to renounce it here, ſhall never be coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted worthy for to judge it, as to denounce againſt it hereafter.</p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>A minori,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Some Authors make hard ſenſe, in making the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> to aſſert this in the affirmative, rather than in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrogare it in the negative. But it is cleare, he argues from ſome diminu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion of their eſteeme; whether proceeding from them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves or others. Doe ye thinke your ſelves <hi>unworthy</hi> to judge theſe ſmaller matters, whom God has thought <hi>worthy</hi> to judge the world? Thats an humility or modeſty reprehenſible (both for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectedneſſe,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:117181:9"/>and puſillanimitie, as alſo for accidie and floathfulneſſe) that ſhall leſſen it ſelfe to Gods gifts and graces, or to the Saints priviledges and Prerogatives; ſo as to make it ſelfe as if it were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meet to doe him ſervice either in Church or Common-wealth. Or elſe, doe others thinke that your holineſſe from God diminiſhes your honour among men? Or that your ſpirituall piety is enough to ſequeſter you from having any hand in ſecular power? Or that your conſcience debarres your reaſon? Or that your faith ſhould blind and corrupt your ſenſe? Or that the Communion of Saints forbids to diſcerne and order things in the common ſociety of men? Can they once imagine that prophane men and Infidels can be more wiſe and juſt (in any matter) then Chriſtians and Saints? Or yet, that a guilty experience is better able to give perfect judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in buſineſſe, then an innocent ſimplicity. I tell you, let a man be experienced or practiſed in a thouſand Caſes, or Cauſes; yet if his Conſcience be guilty or polluted in them, a ſincere enlightened ſoule (who never perhaps heard of the Caſe before) is better able to judge (though not peradventure ſo exactly of the formallity) yet of the very truth and integrity, then is he.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Ab exteriori,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. This word (in Scripture uſe) ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies properly the Judgement Seat. Whereupon he thus inferres, Shall ye ſit upon Thrones above; and muſt you be thought unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to ſit upon Benches here below? But (in the larger accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> deſignes their things; The Senſe, or faculty of judging; the Seat, or place of Judicature; and the Cauſe, or matter to be adjudged. I gather them all into this one obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; That Cauſes are not to be adjudged, but by men of faculty and skill in judgement: nor are they to exerciſe or execute thoſe faculties, but in juſt Callings, or proper places of Judicature.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Ab inferiori,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>the ſmalleſt matters.</hi> That ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is not ſmall enough. For it may well be rendred the moſt baſe, vile, poore, contemptible, infamous, &amp;c. But let us expound it in conſtruction with the former word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and ſo wee obſerve briefly theſe generals: That the skill or faculty of judging here on earth, is a poore rude blindneſſe, and blundering; in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of that perfect and infallible illumination, and diſcretion that ſhall be hereafter: That the ſtatelieſt Seats of Judicature, are
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:117181:10"/>inferiour, nay infamous (footſtooles, nay but as dunghils) to thoſe huge and glorious Thrones. That the matters to be handled now on mans day, are vile and baſe (the beſt of them) in compariſon of thoſe important affaires that ſhall be exactly adjudged and firmely ſetled at that day, when <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhall come with all his Saints. In a word, that if any of theſe be abuſed (by intruſion, ignorance, raſhnes, partiallity, or other corruption) then are they ſmaller then the ſmalleſt, yea viler then the vileſt, and no otherwiſe accounted of in the eſteeme of God and good men, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.3. Wherefore I ſhall draw all of it to this twofold uſe. 1. One to the men of the Law. The matters of your buſineſſe (that I may ſtretch it no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) what be they, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>? You apprehend (I ſuppoſe) the true ſignification. Take heed therefore that you neither over-prize them, nor over-pride your ſelves in them. 2. And then to you Lawing men, What are the things you are given ſo greatly to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend about? <hi>The ſmalleſt matters.</hi> They are your paultry <hi>pence,</hi> for which you ſo (without all <hi>patience</hi>) take your <hi>fellow-Servant</hi> by the <hi>throat,</hi> not once remembring what <hi>compaſſion</hi> your great <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Maſter</hi> has long ſhewne to you, as touching thoſe many <hi>thouſand talents,</hi> whereof you have lived, and (without remiſſion) are likely to dye in the arreares. They are your petty <hi>Treſpaſſes,</hi> for which you regard not to forfeit both the Petition, and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.12, 14. For your carnals you altogether neglect the ſpirituals; and the things pertaining to this life, you wholly ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the things of a better. There's ſuch eagerneſſe in conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for the earth, which was given to the children of men, that there's little earneſtneſſe in contending for the faith, which was once delivered to the Saints of God. And we that are the Saints, or would, or ſhould be, all our judging is (in ſtead of the world) of one another: and that not in the ſmalleſt only, but (woe, and alas!) even in the greateſt matters.</p>
            <p>Having thus abſolved the words and parts of my Text, I come now to my intended point: A point of truth, and of ſuch pertinence to all, as may juſtly require a ſerious Tractate, and not to be taken up by the way, in the latter end of a Sermon only. Had you the patience and I the permiſſion to begin againe, all that were not ſufficient to delineate it in all the numbers of it; yet becauſe I
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:117181:10"/>have already propoſed to diſcover who the Saints are in particular<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And becauſe if we erre and be miſtaken in this, all elſe that has, or can here be ſpoken, is but arrogated, uſurped, and deluſively preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. Therefore I ſhall endeavour in the deſcription both wayes, <hi>viz.</hi> Negatively, and Poſitively, praying you to be content at this time in ſtead of a Syntagme, with a Synopſis only.</p>
            <p n="1">I. Negatively, to ſhew who they are not; for falſhood muſt be removed, ere truth can be planted. Therefore there are to be raced out of the Catalogue of Saints; or rather, not to be there in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolled.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Not they, that are not in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> Phil. 1.1.—<hi>The Saints in Chriſt Ieſus, ſc.</hi> choſen in him, called by him, perfected through him, intended for him, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.2. — <hi>Them that are ſanctified in Chriſt Jeſus, called to be Saints.</hi> Can any man be called to the ſtate and being of a Saint, before he be ſanctified by Chriſts Bloud, Baptiſme, Goſpell, Grace, Merits? unleſſe this foundation be laid, it is impoſſible to raiſe any ſuch like ſuperſtructure; not only for thoſe ſayings, but for theſe reaſons. 1. Becauſe <hi>Chriſt</hi> therefore made himſelfe a Saint, to the end he might ſo make us Saints in himſelfe, <hi>John</hi> 17.19. <hi>For their ſakes I ſanctifie my ſelfe, that they alſo might be ſanctified through the truth</hi> (which indeed is my ſelf.) He ſanctified himſelfe in the aſſumption of his humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; to ſanctifie our nature, in a reconciliation of it to God: He ſanctified himſelfe to the office of his mediation, that ſo he might ſanctifie us to the office of our profeſſion: He ſanctified or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared himſelfe to his paſſion, to the end he might ſanctifie or purge us from our ſins: He ſanctified himſelfe to a perfection of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, to the intent he might ſanctifie us to a conformitie in our lives. 2. Becauſe we were Saints in <hi>Chriſt</hi> before we were Saints, nay while we were yet corrupt in our ſelves. The <hi>lump,</hi> or maſſe, prophane it ſelfe, is notwithſtanding <hi>holy</hi> in the <hi>firſt fruits:</hi> The <hi>Branches wild</hi> in themſelves, are <hi>holy</hi> nevertheleſſe in their <hi>root,</hi> Rom. 11.16, 17. Our <hi>children</hi> that are <hi>uncleane</hi> in themſelves, yet <hi>now are they holy,</hi> 1 Cor. 7.14. and all through the Covenant made with us and our ſeed 3. Becauſe now that we are Saints in our ſelves, we are yet more Saints in Chriſt then we are in our ſelves.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:117181:11"/>'Tis not all our inſpired or preſent, but his preſenting <hi>holineſſe</hi> that makes us ſo purely and perfectly holy, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.27. <hi>Gol.</hi> 1.22. And therefore we count not our Saintſhip to conſiſt ſo much in our active and infuſed, as in our paſſive and imputed ſanctity: For by the one we can be but holy, as we are capable of in our ſelves; but by the other we are found to be holy, as he is holy.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Not they, that have not the ſpirit. We attribute it in pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar manner to the <hi>Holy-Ghoſt,</hi> to be our <hi>Sanctifier</hi> (which is as much as a Saint-maker.) And ſhall any man thinke to be ſo made without his Maker? In <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.4. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.13. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.2. There are theſe convertible termes or Propoſitions; the <hi>Spirit of</hi> ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, and <hi>the ſanctification of the Spirit.</hi> To note both wayes, that neither can that Cauſe be without this effect, nor this effect without that Cauſe. As no <hi>Spirit</hi> without ſanctification, ſo no ſanctification without <hi>the Spirit.</hi> Perſons of Saints, actions of Saints, communion of Saints, all are ſanctified or ſainted by the <hi>Holy-Ghoſt,</hi> the <hi>Spirit</hi> of our God; <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.16. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.21.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Not they, that are not ſanctified by the Word. It is the Word that ſanctifies the common creature, even to ſaintly uſes, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.5. It is the Word that ſanctifies the Perſon to his ſaintly Duties, John 17.17. <hi>Sanctifie them through thy truth, thy word is truth.</hi> Excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding well limited by our <hi>Saviour</hi> himſelfe; that no man might preſume of other, or further ſanctity, or Saintſhip, then the Word it ſelfe ſets forth: Or, that there ſhould be a truth of any thing, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to be knowne or done (by ſanctified men or Saints) either beſides or beyond it. It is by the Word (and by the Sacraments too) that the Church (or Congregation of Saints) is ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, both in her myſterious relations, and religious offices, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.26. Let the <hi>Saints</hi> of the Church then ſee to it, that neither means of ſanctification or Saintſhip be neglected.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Not they, that would be Saints in name only, and in nothing elſe. We read of the <hi>called Saints</hi> indeed, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.7. 1 <hi>Corin.</hi> 1.2. But who expounds that of the Nominall, and not of the reall Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling? In the Old Teſtament, the word <hi>Saint</hi> is ſo indefinite in ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification, that (in many places) we are left to interpret it indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently, either of a <hi>holy man,</hi> or of a <hi>holy thing.</hi> And there (in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:117181:11"/>places againe) the Saints, or holy perſons, are expreſſed by <hi>ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctity,</hi> or holineſſe it ſelfe: yea and <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe is not only cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>Holy One,</hi> but the <hi>Holy thing,</hi> Luke 1.39. All is to teach us, not to glory in the name without the thing: not to bea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of, Saints in the concrete, without ſanctitie in the abſtract. What? ſhall we be as prophane as Papiſts are ſuperſtitious, in calling painted Pictures and liveleſſe Images, Saints? The word was abuſed of old (whether arrogantly or ironically, I know not) by calling whoremongers and hariets by the ſame, or the like name with Saints, <hi>Gen.</hi> 38.21. <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.17. 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 23.7. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.14. I am aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to ſay, how it is ſo and ſo abuſed even now adayes.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Not they, who (out of an opinion of their owne ſanctitie) deſpiſe all others; as if there were no Saints but themſelves. Of this ſect were ſome old <hi>Jewes,</hi> Iſa 65.5. and after them the <hi>Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees,</hi> Luke 7.39. &amp; 18.9. As he cannot be ſimply a Saint, that is a Saint only in compariſon (comparing himſelfe with others, whom he takes to be worſe, or not ſo good as himſelfe;) ſo neither is he, (who comparing himſelfe with himſelfe,) preſumes himſelfe for a Saint alone, or above all other Saints whomſoever. Contrary to ſuch a <hi>Phariſaicall</hi> conceit, was St <hi>Pauls</hi> humble apprehenſion and confeſſion of himſelfe, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.8. <hi>Who am leſſe thou the leaſt of all Saints.</hi> But how doe they make themſelves better then the leaſt of Saints? who thinke it no ſacriledge to reb <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> of the name of Saints, and yet no ſuperſtition to aſſume it to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: Who preſume that their righteouſneſſe then exceeds the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> when they exceed them only in Pharaſciſme: Who not only contemne others, as the <hi>Reſhagaim,</hi> the wicked; and deride the <hi>Thaddikim,</hi> the juſt in a conformity to the Morall Law; but not contented to be accounted the <hi>Cheſidim,</hi> righteous above the Law, in their Traditions; they will be (that I may adde ſo much to the old diſtinction) even the <hi>Kedoſhim,</hi> holy above the Goſpell, in their owne deluſions.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Not they, who make all to be Saints alike, Numb. 16.3. <hi>All the Congregation are holy every one of them.</hi> Oh the arrogance of confuſion I There will be a ſeperation. <hi>The Lord will ſhew who are his, and who are holy,</hi> or Saints. Meane while bring every man his <hi>Cenſor,</hi> his conſcience, and ſtand in the doore of the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:117181:12"/>the Church of God; and be you before the Lord in preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting your conſcience to be informed by his Word; and then the glory of the Lord (his graces) will appeare. Thinke not to fetch Saints (all at once, or one like another) out of the earth; for that were utterly againſt the old Etymology of a Saint, (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) and it is to be feared, the carth will ſwallow up ſuch Saints againe. But look up to the heavens, (whence all Saints have their originall) and you ſhall ſoon perceive the difference, not only bet wixt ſtars and Comets, but even betwixt ſtarres, and ſtarres. For they differ in grace as well as glory, 1 Cor. 15.41.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Not they, which <hi>make warre with the Saints,</hi> Dan. 7.21. Revel. 3.7. Not they, which <hi>give the fleſh of his Saints unto the beaſts of the earth,</hi> Pſal. 79.2. Not they, which are <hi>drunken with the bloud of the Saints,</hi> Revel. 17.6. You know, the places are expounded of Atheiſts, Idolaters, Prophaners, Hypocrites, Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, Schiſmaticks, Perſecutors, &amp;c. and of their cruelties, treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, ſeducements, &amp;c. I read of one (and but of one) of whom it was ſaid, <hi>He had done much evill to the Saints,</hi> Acts 9.13. yet he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards became a Saint; and (as a Saint) ſuffered more himſelfe, than he had done to all others before: and yet (for what he had dome) accounted himſelfe the leaſt of all Saints ever after.</p>
            <p n="2">II. Poſitively, now to ſhew who they are. And I ſhall as ſhortly deſcribe them from their Properties, their Exerciſes, their Priviledges, and their Services.</p>
            <p n="1">1. From their gracious Properties. Were I to define a Saint, I would doe it thus: A Saint is the ſubject of grace; Neither do I take a Saint to be any other thing, than grace in the concrete; or indeed the collective of all graces. His gracious Properties are they which conſtitute him in himſelfe, difference him from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and declare him to all the world. And they are,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Innocence.</hi> This is much uſed in the definition of a Saint, or deſcription. And vulgarly, a Saint and an Innocent, are taken for Synonyma's. It is ſaid of Chriſt, our <hi>High Prieſt,</hi> that hee was <hi>holy, and harmleſſe,</hi> Hebr. 7.26. and ſuch an one became us, both to believe, and imitate. And it is the great act of his Office, not onely to make us <hi>holy, and unblameable;</hi> but to preſerve, and preſent us ſo, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.4. &amp; 5.27. <hi>Col</hi> 1.22. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.9. &amp;
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:117181:12"/>3.13. The places give us to note plainly, That he that is a Saint, or <hi>holy</hi> in his perſon, muſt alſo be an Innocent, or <hi>unblamable</hi> in his actions; and not only ſo, but in his affections alſo, unblamable, or unreprovable, both as from his owne <hi>boars</hi> and conſcience, and <hi>in the ſight of God;</hi> and by the report and <hi>witneſſe</hi> of godly and faithfull men. Neither willingly giving occaſion (as the ſeverall words import) for private ſcandall to complaine, nor for publick juſtice to call in queſtion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Feare of God.</hi> A private feare, or that of conſcience: <hi>O fear the Lord yee his Saints,</hi> Pſal. 34.9. A publick feare, or that of ſervice. <hi>God is greatly to be feared in the aſſembly of the Saints,</hi> Pſalme 89.7. Between this and that, is the whole work of our Chriſtian, or Saintly proficiency; <hi>Perfecting holineſſe in the feare of God,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.1. For holineſſe without feare, ſoone growes ſloathfull in ſrcurity: and fear without holineſſe, growes as ſloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in deſpair. Both theſe therefore having had their perfect work, there wants not their reward, neither temporall, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.9. nor e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall. <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.18.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Faith.</hi> The <hi>Saints</hi> and the <hi>Faithfull</hi> are inſeperable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.1. <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 1.2. And though ſome diſtinguiſh them by their Callings and Degrees, yet I cannot well diſcerne which is one, which another; which is firſt, which laſt: ſaving that he is the one more properly, as juſtified by <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and the other, as ſanctified by the <hi>Holy Ghoſt.</hi> Onely (becauſe many pretend to faith, without holineſſe) I would that the faith of the Saints were diſcerned by the zeale of profeſſion, <hi>Jude</hi> 3. By the vertue of obedience, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.12. by the communion of Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.2. and by the patience of expectation, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.10.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Love.</hi> It either reſpects God and man, or man and man. Betwixt God and man, it is either that love whereby God loved them firſt, and ſo it is the cauſe or ground of their Saintſhip, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.7. <hi>Beloved of God, called to be Saints:</hi> Or elſe it is that love where with they love God againe; and ſo it is the effect, or ſigne of their Saintſhip, <hi>Pſalme</hi> 31.23. <hi>O love the Lord all yee his Saints.</hi> Betwixt man and man, their love is defective to none, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.4.—<hi>Holy and without blame in love:</hi> But exceſſive and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounding to thoſe of their like.—<hi>Your love unto all the Saints. Eph.</hi> 1.15. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.4.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:117181:13"/>5. <hi>Wiſedome.</hi> And that of extraordinary revelation, as touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing particular promiſes, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 89.19. <hi>Thou ſpakeſt in viſion to thy holy one, &amp;c.</hi> Of ordinary illumination, in the perpetuall truth, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.26. <hi>The myſterie which hath been laid from ages, and from generations, is now made manifeſt to his Saints.</hi> The Saints of old exceeded us in legall viſions; but we tranſcend them in Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call illuminations: Our myſterious way comparatively hidden to them; their miraculous way ſuperlatively hidden to us. How great deluſion is it then for us to dote after their miſts, and Moon-ſhine, in the midſt of our owne Sun-ſhine, and perfect day? <hi>Item,</hi> of a diſcreet apprehenſion, in matters of prudent and conſcientious Piety, <hi>Prov.</hi> 9.10.) <hi>The knowledge of the holy</hi> (or of the Saints) <hi>is underſtanding:</hi> None like to theirs for piety and policy, both at once. That of others, is but the ſhadow; this of theirs, is the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of all wiſedome. But where is it to be found? In few, or none: For what hee once ſaid in modeſty, <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.3. every man almoſt may ſay with ſhame; <hi>I have neither learned wiſedome, nor have the knowledge of the holy,</hi> or of the Saints. <hi>Item,</hi> of perfect comprehenſion, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.18.—<hi>may comprehend with all Saints, &amp;c.</hi> Namely, the love of God in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to be comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded (in all the dimenſions of it) by the Saints in heaven. Both <hi>the breadth,</hi> how it extends to all, Saints, and Angells; and <hi>the length,</hi> how it was from everlaſting, to everlaſting; and <hi>the depth,</hi> how it had no cauſe, but that rooted within it ſelfe; and <hi>the height,</hi> how it hath brought them to glory in the higheſt Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Purity.</hi> Both of body and minde. For hee that is no pure Saint in his body (believe it) can bee no true Saint in his ſoule. One that is a right Saint, muſt be <hi>holy both in body and ſpirit,</hi> 1 Cor. 7.34. Nor can there bee any perfecting of holineſſe, till a man have <hi>cleanſed himſelfe from all filthineſſe of the fleſh, and Spirit,</hi> 2 Cor. 7.1. Wherefore, <hi>Yeeld your members ſervants to righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe unto holineſſe,</hi> Rom. 6.19. And <hi>preſent your bodies a living ſacrifice, holy, &amp;c.</hi> Rom. 12.1. <hi>For</hi> this is the will of God, even your <hi>Sanctification,—that every one of you ſhould know how to poſſeſſe his veſſell in ſanctification and honour</hi> 1 Theſ. 4.1, 2. Take heed then (as yee would bee accounted Saints) not onely of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:117181:13"/>actuall pollution, through uncleanneſſe of commiſſion, but even of verball infection, through corrupt communication. <hi>But For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, and all uncleanneſſe, and covetouſneſſe, let it not once be na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med amongſt you, as becommeth Saints,</hi> Eph. 5.3.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Patience.</hi> In <hi>Daniel,</hi> and the <hi>Revelations,</hi> (Dan. 7.21, 25. &amp; 8.24. Rev. 13.7, 10. &amp; 14.12. &amp; 16.6. &amp; 17.6.) much is expreſſed concerning the <hi>patience of the Saints:</hi> And much more might be thence affirmed, both as touching their patience of perpeſſion, and of expectation; of ſufferance, and of perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. And (beſides the kinds) the cauſes alſo (Gods juſtice, and mans injuſtice) as likewiſe faith and obedience, the expreſſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions thereof. But I forbeare, becauſe I know not, whether even your patience will beare it, and whether my words, (if they bee many) may not tire it in the very hearing: or (if theſe words ſhould be weighty) might not (as to the hearing, and bearing) weary it, with impoſing yet further upon it.</p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>Humility.</hi> Which is an humble or lowly apprehenſion of our own graces, and Saintſhip. Both becauſe of all defects in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of God, <hi>Who put no truſt, or found no ſtedfaſtneſſe in his Saints, Job</hi> 15.15. That they ſhould ſtand of themſelves, or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out him, or ſhould be of conſiſtency like to him, or once offer to contend with him: And likewiſe, becauſe of manifold both de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, and exorbitances; in relation not onely to themſelves, but others alſo: Enough (if well laid to heart) to make the beſt Saint ſay ingeniouſly of himſelfe, <hi>I am leſſe than the leaſt of all Saints, Eph.</hi> 3.8. And thinke it honour enough, <hi>to waſh the Saints feet,</hi> 1 Tim. 5.10.</p>
            <p n="2">2. From their gracious Exerciſes. For what barren and emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty notions are thoſe we have of gifts and graces unexerciſed? I ſay, barren, and empty notions; if not bare and aerie pretenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. How were the good and faithfull ſervants to bee differenced from that wicked and ſloathfull one, but by the imployment, and improvement of their Talents? He had his Talent, but he hid it in the earth, or laid it up in a Napkin; whereas they traded with theirs, and gained double to them. The true Saint then is to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed, and declared by his exerciſes: which are,</p>
            <p n="1">1. To endeavour in the diſcerning, or putting a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:117181:14"/>
               <hi>holy</hi> and <hi>unholy, Levit.</hi> 10.10. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 44.23. Namely, both men, and things. For he who ſtudies not to diſcerne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt holy and unholy things, ſhall never be able to diſcerne true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by betwixt holy and unholy men. Neither are we to conſider the thing by the man, but the man by the thing: For the trees are known by their fruit, and not the fruit by their trees. And without this diſcretion (in ſome meaſure) neither can a duty bee done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right by any man; nor judged rightly of, when done by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To labour diligently in univerſall obedience to Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements. For certainly, no obedience, no Saint: Becauſe this is the expreſſe condition of the Saints initiating, <hi>Exod.</hi> 19.5, 6. his avouching, <hi>Deut.</hi> 26.17, 18. his eſtabliſhing, <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.9. and his conſummating, <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.12, 13.</p>
            <p n="3">3. To imitate God, and Chriſt, eſpecially in holineſſe, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.15, 16. <hi>As he which hath called you is holy, ſo bee yee holy in all manner of converſation. Becauſe it is written, be yee holy; for I am holy.</hi> God is eſſentially, independantly, and infinitely holy; and in all theſe wayes his holineſſe is to us unimitable: He gives us here a command to be holy, and that binds us onely to bee ſo, but helps us not. He likewiſe ſets forth to us his owne being holy (yet as a propoſed motive, not a proportioned modell) and that urges us moreover, but nevertheleſſe aſſiſts us not. But he alſo here gives us our Call to be holy; and the Call invites graciouſly, as well as the command juſtly obliges. For here he gives us a patterne, as well as there a rule; propoſing him that hath called us, for our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, ſtretching it not beyond our owne converſation, and capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, although inlarging it to the utmoſt of it ſelf. And ſo we have the grace and power, aid and incouragement, rule and guid, means and way for our imitation.</p>
            <p n="4">4. To labour in, and after Communion; <hi>The Communion of Saints,</hi> as it is of the Members with their head, ſo it is among the Priviledges: but as it is of the Members each with other, ſo it is amongſt the exerciſes of Saints. This we glory in, as a Priviledge; but we faile of it, as an exerciſe. Therefore is it neceſſary to ſay, firſt, how it is erred in; next how it ought to be endeavoured af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. 1. The errours are, that men are over-ſpeculative, and not
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:117181:14"/>practicall enough in this point. They think that they have ſatisfied this truth to aſſent unto it, or profeſſe it as an Article of their Creed, though they never endeavour it in the practice of their converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Whereas indeed, no man can rightly believe, that there is a Communion of Saints, much leſſe that himſelfe is one of that Communion, unleſſe he be duely exerciſed therein: That ſome men ſtretch it too high, and farre, and wide, and ſo make it a commixi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or indeed a confuſion, rather than a Communion: That ſome tie it up too ſtraight, and would ſeeme to purge it ſo preciſely, as that (inſtead of any thing like to ſociety) they make it the ſame with a ſeparation, a ſingularity, or very ſolitude it ſelfe: That ſome will be admitting ſuch as are no Saints; and ſome againe will not admit of very Saints into their Communions: That ſome make it to conſiſt in a communitie of goods, more than in a communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of graces; and in a Congregation of bodies, not in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction of ſoules; and a conſpiracy of rude members, not har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of holy powers; and a communication of tongues and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, more than any co-union of hearts and minds: That ſome will be intruding themſelves into a particular, and familiar Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, even with the Saints in heaven; and ſome are ſhye of other, than a generall and call'd communion with the Saints on earth. 2. The endeavours here ought to be according to theſe regulations of it. Not ſimply to have communion one with another; but with ſpeciall relation to our union with Chriſt, and his Spirit, the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and foundation of all our Saintly communion, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.3.7. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17. &amp; 12.13. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.14. Not to abandon utterly all externall communion with wicked men and hypocrites; and yet not to admit them into the internal neither, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.9, 10, 13. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.22. Not to break off all communion with a Brother, for every infirmity or offence; and yet not to communicate with the ſinnes of any, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.14, 15. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.11. Not to have reſpect of perſons in Chriſtian Communion, as touching Nation, Sex, Age, Degree, Condition, &amp;c. and yet even there alſo to prefer one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore another, for their meaſures, and eminences ſake, <hi>James</hi> 2.1, 2, 3. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.28. &amp; 2.9. Not to think that our communion (either with the Head or Members) can be perfected all at once; but to labour in the completion of it by times and degrees, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.15,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:117181:15"/>&amp; <hi>Col.</hi> 2.19. Plainly, and in few; to labour after this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, by the meanes of the Word, Sacraments and Prayer, &amp;c. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.19. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.13. &amp; 10.16, 17. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.4, 5. To labour in this communion, by communicating our gifts and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.11. <hi>Philem.</hi> 5, 6. By teaching and exhorting both by Word and Example, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.3. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.6. By communicating to one anothers outward neceſſities, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.13. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.4. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.15. By conforming our ſelves to <hi>Chriſt</hi> in our owne ſufferings; and compaſſionating others in theirs, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.13. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.14. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.7.</p>
            <p n="5">5. To have the divine Ordinances in due obſervation. I paſſe by thoſe that were particular, and temporary, <hi>Exo.</hi> 22.30, 31. <hi>Lev.</hi> 21.6. <hi>Numb.</hi> 6.5. I ſpeake only of two Ordinances, which are univerſall, and perpetuall throughout the Church of Chriſt. That is to ſay, the Magiſtracy, and the Miniſterie: both which all the Saints (as Saints) are bound to obſerve, becauſe ordained of God, and for their good. 1. The Magiſtracy; <hi>All his Saints are in thy hands, they ſate downe at thy feet, every one ſhall receive of thy words. Deut.</hi> 33.3. They are the words either of God, approving <hi>Moſes</hi> his authority to his People; or of <hi>Moſes</hi> commending the Peoples obſervance; or elſe of the People, acknowledging him, and themſelves in both theſe: and that as touching both their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, Subjection, and Direction. 2. The Miniſtery; <hi>He gave ſome Apoſtles, and ſome Prophets, and ſome Evangeliſts, and ſome Paſtors, and Teathers; for the perfecting of the Saints, Epheſ.</hi> 4.11, 12. There is this one end of all kinde of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters Inſtitution; the Saints perfection. How can the Saints then be perfect without them? The originall word there imports how laxate, or looſe-joynted they are, if theſe be wanting to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme them; worthy therefore they are to be obſerved by all ſuch, and if it bee but for their workes ſake, as it eſpecially concernes themſelves.</p>
            <p n="6">6. To apply earneſtly unto Prayer. A prime exerciſe of Saints, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.2. So ſoone as <hi>called to be Saints,</hi> immediately <hi>calling upon the name of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> This I ſay therefore, no praying people, no Saints; yet ſay I not, that every one is a Saint that prayes. No, not any one, unleſſe he pray, 1. In, and by the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:117181:15"/>
               <hi>Spirit. He maketh interceſſion for the Saints,</hi> Rom. 8.27. 2. As vold of ſuperſtition, <hi>in every place;</hi> ſo void of ſingularity: remembring that <hi>Chriſt</hi> is others Lord, as well as his owne, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.2. 3. Upon other Saints, or holy mens occaſion and example, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.6. 4 In the harmony or conſent of all faculties, with the clearneſſe of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and zeale of affections. All noted by the <hi>Harps, gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den vialls,</hi> and <hi>odours;</hi> which are ſaid to be <hi>the prayers of the Saints, Rev.</hi> 5.8. 5. In the name of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who is <hi>the Angell offering up the prayers of the Saints,</hi> in the <hi>golden Cenſer</hi> of his owne me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits and mediation, <hi>Rev.</hi> 8.3, 4.</p>
            <p n="7">7. To give hearty thanks and praiſe to God, <hi>viz.</hi> publikely, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately; for all his gracious acts, and according to all his gracious attributes: Out of a bounden duty, a ready mind, a chearfull voice, a comely order, and a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>it opportunity, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 30.4. &amp; 52.9. &amp; 89.5. &amp; 145.10.149.1.</p>
            <p n="8">8. To deſire, and endeavour in a proficiency of all holy duties. Both by a vigilant circumſpection againſt temptations and relap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. <hi>He will ſpeake peace unto his people, and to his Saints; but let them not turne agains to folly,</hi> Pſalme 85.8. As alſo in a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall augmentation, and proceſſion, both of graces, and duties. <hi>He that is holy, let him be holy ſtill,</hi> Rev. 22.11.</p>
            <p n="3">III. From their Priviledges. Whereof ſome are to ſet forth their dignity, and advancement, in honourable Titles: Some their advantage, or utility, in ineſtimable benefits.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Thoſe of their advancement in Dignity: Beſides that, they are uſually ſtiled a <hi>holy people, choſen, ſpeciall, peculiar, redeemed, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed, ſought out, beloved,</hi> &amp;c. God has promiſed to make them high above all other, <hi>in praiſe, in name,</hi> and <hi>in honour,</hi> Deut. 26.19. That is, for goodneſſe, power and eſteeme. And God is as good as his word; <hi>He exalteth the horne of his people, the praiſe of all his Saints,</hi> Pſalme 148.14. <hi>ſc.</hi> makes them the praiſe and admiration of all people; that they may praiſe and adore him the more. More particularly, He hath made them to be <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Prieſts,</hi> or a <hi>Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Prieſthood,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.6. A Royall Prieſthood, in aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milation to <hi>Chriſt;</hi> the Prieſt of the Royall, not the rigid Law. A Kingdome wherein is a Prieſthood; for ſervice and holineſſe: and a Prieſthood, wherein is a Kingdome; for authority and order:
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:117181:16"/>Kings, in the juſtice of Civill government: Prieſts, in the mercy of Eccleſiaſticall government: Kings, to ſubdue carnall corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: Prieſts, to offer ſpirituall ſacrifices: Kings, againſt the adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries of the Church: Prieſts, towards the Sonnes of the Church: Prieſts to ſerve here, and Kings to raigne hereafter. I adde (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the occaſion) Judges, and Counſellors: Judges, both againſt the enemies of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> in generall, <hi>Jude</hi> 14, 15. and againſt their owne enemies and perſecuters in particular, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.21, 22. Counſellors, to which we may <hi>turne.</hi> Job 5.1. He means not to dead Saints, by way of Invocation; but to living Saints, for Patronage, and Advocateſhip; for counſell, and advice; for infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, and inſtruction; for inſtance, and example. And hereupon, let me not adde to ſay; no Saints, no Judges; no Saints, no Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Thoſe of their advantage, or benefit; which be, 1. To be ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially protected, both in body and ſoule; againſt evils both internall, and externall. <hi>The Lord forſaketh not his Saints, they are preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for ever,</hi> Pſalme 37.28. <hi>He preſerveth the ſoules of his Saints,</hi> Pſalme 97.10. <hi>He will keep the feet of his Saints,</hi> 1 Sam. 2.9. 2. To be peaceably comforted, both againſt the conſcience of ſinne: <hi>He will ſpeake peace to his Saints,</hi> &amp;c. Pſalme 85.8. As alſo in the tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity of a good conſcience; <hi>Let the Saints be joyfull in glory, let them ſing aloud upon their beds,</hi> Pſalme 149.5. And that, in the comforts and chearfulneſſe, both of graces and duties, 2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 6.41. <hi>Pſalme</hi> 132.9, 10. 3. To be eternally ſaved. It is verified not of our <hi>Saviour</hi> only, but of every Saint; <hi>Thou wilt not ſuffer thy Holy One to ſee corruption,</hi> Pſalme 16.10. <hi>The Saints poſſeſſed the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> Dan. 7.22. There's their injoying of it. <hi>The riches of the glory of his inheritance in the Saints,</hi> Eph. 1.18. There's <hi>Chriſt</hi> injoying of them; <hi>Partakers of the inheritance of the Saints in light,</hi> Col. 1.12. There's their enjoying of one another in him.</p>
            <p n="4">4. From their Services: I meane ſuch as are due unto them, not only from one another, but ſome of them from all other. And (in briefe) they are, 1. The praying for one another, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.18. 2. The viſiting or ſaluting one another, <hi>Acts</hi> 9.32. <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.15. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.13. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.21, 22. 3. The loving, and reverencing one anothers Perſons, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.15. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.4. <hi>Mark</hi> 6.20. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.10.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:117181:16"/>4. The delighting in one anothers company, and communion, <hi>Pſalme</hi> 16.3. &amp; <hi>Pſalme</hi> 18.26. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 11.12. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.19. 5. The ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtring to one anothers neceſſities, <hi>Pſalme</hi> 16.2, 3. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.13. &amp; 15.25, 26, 31. &amp; 16.2. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.1, 15. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.4. &amp; 9.1. <hi>Phile.</hi> 7. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 6.10. Should I inſiſt to explaine all theſe ſervices, as they are laid forth (for our rules and examples) in the aforeſaid places; and (in particular) examine how they are performed by one, or other, I ſhould bring in the world (I feare) to judge the Saints in theſe neglects. And for all theſe (with many more that might be apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the whole diſcovery) there be many, who though they preſume themſelves for Saints, and ſuch as ſhall judge the world; yet ſhall they find themſelves (I am afraid) judged amongſt the worſt of the world, at the great day of God.</p>
            <p>Now the good God of Heaven doe away the vayles, and more then menſtruous raggs of ſimulated ſanctitie, and cloath us with the <hi>fine linnen</hi> (the perfection of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi>) which is <hi>the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Saints,</hi> Rev. 19.8. And abate the arrogance and teme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of judging before the time: And make us ſo <hi>to judge our ſelves,</hi> that we may not be <hi>judged.</hi> And ſo to judge the world now, in the ſincerity of grace, that we may judge it hereafter in the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of glory. And <hi>when we are judged</hi> here, we may be ſo <hi>chaſtened of the Lord:</hi> And when we are judged hereafter, we may be ſo ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved by him, as that we may juſtly condemne, and never be juſtly <hi>condemned with the world,</hi> 1 Cor. 11.31, 32.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
